we surveyed developers a few months ago
asking which tasks they thought agents were best suited to perform today
the second most answered one
was personal assistance and productivity tasks
one core aspect of these tasks
is memory specifically long-term memory
think about working with a human assistant
who is serving as a personal assistant of sorts
if they forgot all their conversations with you
and didn't remember things that you told them previously
that would be a pretty bad experience
and the same goes for agents
so memory is a key part of these types of tasks
and so when we think about an example
through which to introduce memory
a task of this nature is a great fit
one example of a task like this is an email agent
so email is something that we all have
and we all have to deal with
and as you get busier and busier
you may have more and more emails popping up
that you just don't have time to look at or respond to
and this is perfect for an agent to come in
if we think about what an agent would need to do this job well
it's probably pretty similar to what an executive assistant
might need to do this job well
they might need calendar to check your calendar
to see where you're free
and they might need access to writing emails
on your behalf or in response to other emails
and so when we think about building an agent
we can think about giving them
access to these types of tools
and an agent like this has a lot of places
where memory becomes really important
first step is looking at all the emails
and deciding
should i ignore this
should i respond to this
if it does decide to respond to it
and decides to use the calendar or email tool
it needs to know
what is the person's meeting preferences
both in terms of time
but also location and title
and then if it decides to write an email
it needs to know
what is this person's tone
what is their style
and then there might also be
interactions with people
that they've had previously
this is important context
to be able to know
to respond to
and so this email assistant
is a great place
to show off
what llms
and memory
can do together
and so we're going to use it
as a proving ground
for talking about
three different types
of memory
for ai agents
so first is semantic memory
so what is semantic memory
it's basically facts
if we think about semantic memory
in humans
it's things that you've learned
facts that you've learned in school
by reading a textbook
that you remember
from previous interactions
all these kind of like
facts based type
of memory
a second type of memory
is episodic memory
this is experiences
this is calls backs
to exact conversations
that you've had
it's not necessarily
facts about these conversations
it's just the memory
of this conversation itself
the memory
of going to disneyland
something like that
and the third type of memory
is procedural memory
these are kind of like
instructions for yourself
or instincts
or motor skills
how to ride a bike
or instructions that you give yourself
for how to respond
to emails
for example
how do we map these
onto agents
so for semantic memory
these might be facts
about a user
or about people
placed things
that the agent
has interacted with
for episodic
this might be past
agent actions
so in the form
of few shot examples
so actual
literal kind of like
trajectories
of what have happened
before
and then for procedural
this is maybe the most
strateforward
this is a system prompt
the instructions
that you give the agent
on how to behave
besides these three types
of memories
it's also worth
calling out the different
ways that these agents
can interact with
these memories
so there's two
different paradigms
that we see
one is generally
in the hotpath
so this is where
the agent updates
memories
as it's responding
to the user
so it's all
in one go
a separate type
is when the updates
of the memory
happen in the background
or in a separate
process
there's pros
and cons
to each of these
when you update
things in the hotpath
you generally
just have one agent
and so that's
simpler to maintain
and the updates
often happen
instantaneously
however
the downside is
that you now
have
this agent
that has to
do both
these things
that has to
update memories
and responds
to users
so it's more
complicated
and it also
adds an additional
latency
when responding
to the user
and the background
has the flip
so now you can
separate the
update of memory
from the
agent's core
things that it
needs to do
so it's simpler
and you remove
the updating
from the hotpath
so it actually
responds faster
the issue is
that now you
have two agents
instead of one
so that's more
complicated
and the updates
might not happen
instantaneously
they might only
happen when
the updating
memory gets
kicked off
so in this
course we are
going to apply
these memory
types to an
email agent
so we're going
to start with
a basic
email agent
that first
triages the
incoming emails
and if it's
worth responding
to it passes
it on to a
second agent
which uses a
calendar tool
and a writing
tool to respond
to the email
the first type
of memory
that we're going
to add in
is semantic
memory
and so we're
going to do
this by giving
this agent
that's responding
to emails
more tools
tools for
writing memories
and tools for
reading memories
the agent's going
to use these
tools in the
hotpath
so as it's
looping and
as it's calling
the calendar
or writing the
email it's going
to be writing
memories and
retrieving
memories
so this is
semantic memory
in the hotpath
and we're doing
this by giving
the agent
a tool
then we're
going to add
episodic memory
so this is in
the form of
few shot
examples that
are going to
be in the
triage step
so here we're
going to have
few shot
examples
that correspond
to emails
and then it's
also going to
have what we
want the
triage result
to be so
whether it
should be
ignored or
notified or
responded to
and so these
are going to
be inserted into
the prompt
right here
we're going to
add these
examples in a
separate process
so this is an
example of
episodic memory
where the
updates happen
in the
background
and finally
we're going to
add in
procedural
memory
so these are
the prompts
themselves or
r rather parts
of the prompts
with instructions
for how to
use different
tools or how
to triage
things
we're going
to update
this in the
background as
well and
we're actually
going to use
a separate
agent to do
the updates
although we're
working with a
very specific
email agent
which we're
going to build
in lesson
two the
techniques for
managing agent
memory that you
learn here will
be applicable to
any agents that
you build in
the future
you'll want to
think carefully
about what
types of
memories your
agent needs
does it need to
learn better
instructions okay
maybe that's
procedural do you
want to give it
few shot examples
because you think
that will help
really guide its
actions okay
that's episodic
does it just
need to know
facts about
people place
and things
okay that's
semantic
it all kind of
depends on the
application that
you're building
with that
let's jump to
the next lesson
and learn how
to build this
baseline email
agent